{"tossups": [{"question": "Description acceptable. A TV series inspired the name of Operation Yashima, a plan to conserve energy in the wake of this disaster. In the aftermath of this natural disaster, the new derogatory term\u201cflyjin\u201d was applied to fleeing foreigners. Operation Tomodachi was the American relief e\u21b5ort after this event, which triggered the Miyagi aftershock a month later. Nearly 16,000 people died in, for the point, what 2011 natural disaster that caused a Level 7 meltdown at a Japanese nuclear plant?", "answer": "2011<b> Tohoku earthquake and/or tsunami</b> (accept descriptions of the 2011<b> earthquake and/or tsunami</b> that caused the<b> Fukushima</b> Daiichi nuclear disaster; prompt on descriptions of 2011 earthquake and/or tsunami in Japan that don\u2019t include Tohoku or Fukushima; accept<b> Great East Japan earthquake and/or tsunami</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man argued that governments should provide food if they expected citizens to obey laws in his <em>Plan of Criminal Legislation</em>. This man, who was brought before the Revolutionary Tribunal for inciting violence against the Girondins, noted that \u201cfive or six hundred heads cut o\u21b5would have assured [...] freedom and happiness\u201d in his newspaper<em> Friend of the People</em>. This advocate for the<em> sans-culottes</em> was stabbed by Charlotte Corday and died in his bathtub in 1793. For the point, name this radical journalist of the French Revolution whose death is depicted in a Jacques-Louis David painting", "answer": "Jean-Paul<b> Marat</b> (accept Death of<b> Marat</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Note: two answers required. C.S. Lewis\u2019<em> The Abolition of Man</em> warns against debunking an objective theory of these two concepts, stating that they are fundamental to the idea of education. Spinoza describes the knowledge of these two concepts as \u201cnothing else but the emotions of pleasure or pain.\u201d An 1886 work by Friedrich Nietzsche claims to be a \u201cPrelude to a Philosophy of the Future\u201d by going<em> Beyond</em> these two concepts. Ethicists study the nature of, for the point, what opposing philosophical concepts, commonly personified in literature and art as angels and demons?", "answer": "<b> good and evil</b> (accept word forms; accept reasonable equivalents, such as<b> right and wrong</b>; accept<b> Beyond Good and Evil</b> after \u201c1886\u201d is read) Page 1", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "In this state, the Manly brothers were forced to abandon their<em> Daily Record</em> newspaper after a violent coup destroyed their property and installed Alfred Waddell as mayor. On February 1, 1960, Joseph McNeil and Ezell Blair were part of a group of four A&T students who were refused service at a Woolworth lunch counter in this state, sparking a sit-in campaign and boycott that lasted over five months. The Wilmington insurrection of 1898 and the Greensboro sit-ins took place in, for the point, what southern state where poll taxes and literacy tests were agreed to in the state legislature in Raleigh?", "answer": "<b> North Carolina</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Akos Eleod designed this city\u2019s Memento Park, a resting place for old statues built during Communist rule. This city contains the islands of Margaret, Csepel [cheh-pell], and Obudai, the last of which holds the massive Sziget [sih-get] music festival every August. The Gellert Hill overlooks this city and served as an important vantage point during a 100 day siege in World War II. The Chain bridge and Arpad bridge are located in this city, whose Heroes\u2019 Square is the resting place of Imre Nagy [nahj], the leader of an anti-Soviet 1956 revolution. The Danube River runs through, for the point, what capital of Hungary?", "answer": "<b> Budapest</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name this Whig politician and war hero who served as the ninth president of the US for a month before being succeeded by John Tyler.", "answer": "<b> W</b>illiam Henry<b> Harrison</b> (prompt on<b> Harrison</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During a meeting in this city, Vito Genovese was beaten by a man who was then deported to Italy when the American authorities learned he was in the Western Hemisphere. This city was occupied by revolutionary forces in 1958 in the wake of the Battle of Santa Clara. The fortresses of La Cabana and Morro Castle guard the harbor to this city, whose Hotel Nacional was the site of a 1946 meeting of mob bosses honoring Lucky Luciano. This city was a nightlife destination in the 1950s until a US embargo began in 1960. For the point, name this capital of Cuba.", "answer": "<b> Havana</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One method for accomplishing this procedure relies on examining light intensity upon pyrophosphate release. George Church\u2019s group developed the Polony method for performing this procedure. The \u201cshotgun\u201dmethod for performing this procedure proved more efficient than the chain termination method developed by Frederick Sanger. The NIH and the Celera Corporation competed to fully perform this action on the human genome, which was declared complete in 2003. For the point, name this procedure that determines the order of nucleotides in a genome.", "answer": "DNA<b> sequencing</b> (accept genome<b> sequencing</b>; prompt on descriptions of mapping the genome)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "A plaque on the Sedgeford Hall Portrait falsely claims that the painting depicts this woman. Linwood Custalow claims that this woman was assaulted during her stay in Henricus. The Virginia Racial Integrity Act had an \u201cException\u201d named for this woman that prevented a certain group from being subject to anti-miscegenation laws. Tomocomo accompanied this woman on a 1616 trip to Europe with her husband, John Rolfe. For the point, name this daughter of Powhatan, a Native American woman who befriended the settlers at Jamestown.", "answer": "<b> Pocahontas</b> (accept<b> Matoaka</b>; accept<b> Amonute</b>; accept<b> Rebecca Rolfe</b> before Rolfe is said; prompt on Rebecca alone beforeRolfe is said, and<b> Rebecca</b> alone at that point)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "These people revolted after the issuance of the Seven Grievances. They were unified under the Eight Banners system of Nurhaci. The Revolt of the Three Feudatories targeted a ruler of this ethnicity, shortly after Dorgon led troops of this ethnicity to victory in the Battle of the Shanhai Pass. The longest reigning emperor of China, Kangxi [kahng-shee], was of this ethnicity. The Ming dynasty was overthrown by, for the point, what northern ethnic group that established the Qing [ching] dynasty?", "answer": "<b> Manchu</b> people Page 3", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Apollodorus of Damascus was a military engineer for this man and designed a structure named for him that includes the Basilica Ulpia. A statue of this man was replaced by one of Saint Peter, standing on top of a monument to this man decorated with reliefs culminating in the suicide of Decebalus. This man built a bridge over the Danube River in his most famous campaign. For the point, name this second of the Five Good Emperors who commemorated his conquest of Dacia with a namesake column.", "answer": "<b> Trajan</b> (or Caesar Nerva<b> Trajan</b>us Germanicus or Marcus Ulpius Nerva<b> Trajan</b>us Augustus; do not accept or prompt on any single name that isn\u2019t \u201cTrajan\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This city was the site of a 1953 worker\u2019s rebellion commemorated by the June 17 Day of Unity. Lucius Clay served as commanding officer in this city during a tank stando\u21b5in 1961. This city was the site of several closed subway stations that became known as \u201cghost stations.\u201d The Four Power Agreement guaranteed travel to this city, which contained Checkpoint Charlie. Ronald Reagan asked Mikhail Gorbachev to \u201ctear down\u201d a structure in, for the point, what European capital city that was divided by a namesake wall?", "answer": "<b> Berlin</b> (accept East<b> Berlin</b> throughout; accept West and/or East<b> Berlin</b> after Lucius Clay is said)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A former school in this state near San Ildefonso was converted into a facility that contains Bathtub Row and which was once called \u201cSite Y.\u201d The McDonald Ranch House is located in this state\u2019s White Sands Missile Range, which is near the town of Alamagordo and was the site of an event for which the\u201cJumbo\u201d containment vessel was built. Trinity, the world\u2019s first nuclear test, was detonated here and designed in its Los Alamos Laboratory. For the point, name this southwestern state whose capital is Santa Fe.", "answer": "<b> New Mexico</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was removed from a post after testifying against Orvil Grant in the Trader Post scandal. In his early career, this man served as the aide for Alfred Pleasonton, who gave this man command of the Wolverine cavalry brigade during the Civil War. The Battle of the Rosebud prevented George Crook from joining up with this man, who was killed by the forces of Sitting Bull. For the point, name this American army officer who died in a namesake \u201cLast Stand\u201d at Little Bighorn.", "answer": "George Armstrong<b> Custer</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This state faced a rebellion by the Hotak Dynasty after its governor, Gurgin Khan, was assassinated. This state lost the Battle of Chaldiran, starting a long series of wars with its western neighbor. This state began after the defeat of the White Sheep by a man who commanded the Qizilbash warriors; that leader proclaimed his rule when he entered Tabriz. Another ruler of this empire moved its capital to Esfahan and recovered parts of Mesopotamia from the Ottoman Empire. For the point, name this Shi\u2019a state ruled by leaders like Ismail and Abbas in Persia.", "answer": "<b> Safavid</b> Empire (prompt on Persia before mentioned) Page 4", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this campaign, William Scurry was able to use weights and water tins to invent a self-firing rifle. During this campaign\u2019s bloodiest day, an attack on Hill 60 was launched simultaneously with Beauvoir de Lisle\u2019s assault up Scimitar Hill. In its early stages, one commander in this campaign told his men \u201cI do not order you to fight, I order you to die.\u201d This campaign began with Commonwealth troops landing at Anzac Cove. Winston Churchill planned, for the point, what 11-month campaign of World War I in which Ataturk\u2019s Ottomans successfully defended the Dardanelles Strait?", "answer": "<b> Gallipoli</b> Campaign (or<b> Dardanelles</b> Campaign; accept Battle of<b> Gallipolli</b> and other equivalent terms; accept Battle of<b> Canakkale</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event is the subject of the memoir<em> The Passing of the Armies</em>, which was derided by historian William Marvel as a self-promoting legend. One participant at this event allegedly remarked to a Seneca adjutant that \u201cit is good to have one real American here.\u201d After a cannonball struck his old house, Wilmer McLean relocated, only to have his new home serve as the location of this event. This event\u2019s terms, which guaranteed no prosecutions for treason, were put forth by Ulysses S. Grant. For the point, name this 1865 event that ended the Civil War.", "answer": "<b> surrender</b> at<b> Appomattox</b> Court House (or Robert E.<b> Lee\u2019s surrender</b>; accept any additional correct information; prompt on descriptions of the Confederates surrendering, or \u201c(the end of) the Civil War\u201d before said at the end)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this war, Manie Maritz massacred thirty five members of the Khoikhoi tribe in the Leliefontein Massacre. \u201cRemember Majuba\u201d became a rallying cry in this war, whose popularity in Europe allowed Lord Salisbury to win the first khaki election. Emily Hobhouse exposed, and the Fawcett Commission confirmed, the use of concentration camps under Lord Kitchener in this war. Louis Botha led guerrilla warriors against the British in, for the point, what early 20th century war over the Transvaal in South Africa?", "answer": "Second Anglo-<b>Boer</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One king of this name was dominated by powerful ministers like William de la Pole and the Duke of Gloucester [GLOSS-ter] due to his mental instability; that husband of Margaret of Anjou lost his throne after the Battle of Tewkesbury. Another king of this name ordered the deaths of Lambert Simnel and Perkin Warbeck, two pretenders to his throne; that king of this name won his throne after winning the Battle of Bosworth Field against Richard III. For the point, give this name of the English kings whose reigns began and ended the Wars of the Roses.", "answer": "<b> Henry</b> (accept<b> Henry VI</b> and/or<b> Henry VII</b>) Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this city, Macon Bolling Allen and Robert Morris founded America\u2019s first black law office. Morris argued the trial of Anthony Burns in this city, which led to the formation of its Anti-Man Hunting League. Morris argued unsuccessfully against desegregated schools in<em> Roberts v</em> this city, which laid the foundation for the \u201cseparate but equal\u201d doctrine. In this city, William Lloyd Garrison burned the Constitution. Thomas Preston was acquitted following the shooting of Crispus Attucks and four other colonists in, for the point, what city, home to a 1770 massacre?", "answer": "<b> Boston</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Protesters during Loyalty Day demanded the release of a person with this last name who, ten years later, was attacked during the Bombing of Plaza de Mayo. Another person with this last name went on the diplomatic Rainbow Tour. Followers of a political family with this last name were known as the <em>descamisados</em>. One person with this last name was titled the \u201cSpiritual Leader of the Nation\u201d before dying of cancer in 1952. For the point, name this last name of Juan and Eva, who once were the ruling couple of Argentina.", "answer": "<b> Per\u00b4on</b> (accept Juan and/or Eva<b> Per\u00b4on</b>; accept Evita<b> Per\u00b4on</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s fascist movement was known as Rexism and was led by L\u00b4eon Degrelle. This country\u2019s Dyle River formed the basis for Maurice Gamelin\u2019s defensive plans, and its fortress of Eben-Emael was captured by paratroopers during Case Yellow. World War I fighting in this country included the first use of chlorine gas during the Battle of Ypres [eep]. For the point, name this country invaded by Germany during both World Wars as part of the invasion of France.", "answer": "<b> Belgium</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Potential sites for this location were outlined in the Fall-Davis Report. Many architectural designs at this location were overseen by Gordon Kaufmann. Frank Crowe was the leader of a construction project at this location that was undertaken by a collective called the Six Companies. The name of this location was protested at its dedication by Harold Ickes, as he preferred a name referencing the nearby Boulder Canyon. For the point, name this hydroelectric plant completed in 1936 along the Colorado River.", "answer": "<b> Hoover Dam</b> (accept<b> Boulder Dam</b> before read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In 2012, players of this game requested a game official who spoke Mandarin Chinese and won $9.6 million from the Borgata by edge-sorting; in 2016, a New Jersey district judge ruled that money had to be paid back by poker professional Phil Ivey. This game originated as<em> chemin de fer</em> in France and, in the original Ian Fleming novels, is the casino game preferred by James Bond. In this game, face cards are worth zero and a score of 9 is the highest hand value. For the point, name this card game between player and banker, currently the dominant form of gambling in casinos in Macau.", "answer": "North American<b> baccarat</b> (accept<b> punto banco</b>; do not accept or prompt on chemin de fer or baccarat banque) Page 7", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "One part of this agreement was opposed by a mayor who called it \u201ca dark cloud over the city.\u201d A physician killed 29 people in a house of worship in response to this agreement in the Cave of the Patriarchs Massacre. The Wye River Memorandum aimed to continue implementing this agreement. A photograph shows the leaders of the two parties involved in this agreement shaking hands, with Bill Clinton standing between them. For the point, name this set of agreements between Israel and the Palestine Liberation Organization that is named for a Scandinavian capital city.", "answer": "<b> Oslo</b> Accords (accept<b> Oslo</b> I Accord; accept<b> Oslo</b> II Accord) Page 8", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}